## Adam N. Goodkind

CONTACT Information Northwestern University Department of Communication Studies 2240 Campus Drive, Evanston, IL 60208 USA  ${\it a.goodkind@u.northwestern.edu} \\ {\it adamgoodkind.com}$ 

RESEARCH STATEMENT I study social interactions through the lens of keystroke timing, using HCI theories in combination with linguistic analysis. My thesis is titled *Using keystrokes to predict social dynamics in online dialogue*. It identifies how we can use timing differences in keystrokes to recover many of the same social cues we usually detect in signals such as tone-of-voice or pauses, but are lost in text-based digital communication. The thesis brings together HCI, Cognitive Science, NLP and statistical modeling. I have a passion for applying findings from HCI to creating more useful tools for users, alongside creating engaging visualizations to improve understanding.

EDUCATION

### PhD, Northwestern University

# Media, Technology & Society Program

2019-Present

PI: Darren Gergle (CollabLab)

Dissertation: Using keystrokes to predict social dynamics in online dialogue

### Linguistics Department

2016-2019

PI: Klinton Bicknell (Language & Computation Lab)

Honors:

Data Science Fellowship Cognitive Science Specialist

### M.A., CUNY Graduate Center

2016

Computational Linguistics

M.A. Thesis: Utilizing Linguistic Context To Improve Identification in Typed Text Thesis Advisors: Prof. Andrew Rosenberg and Prof. Martin Chodorow

#### B.A., Columbia University

2007

Religion (Study of Science & Religion)

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# Research Assistant, CollabLab, Evanston, IL, USA

2019-Present

PI: Darren Gergle

- Running a crowd-sourced experiment for my dissertation utilizing keystroke-level analysis to understand social and cognitive differences in production timing and linguistic choices, depending on the social perceptions of a partner in a collaborative task.
- Supervise a Research Assistant tasked with creating a code base and setting up a database.
- Analyze patterns of conversational turn-taking, depending on the social function of an utterance as well as linguistic aspects of the utterances.

#### Research Assistant, LangComp Lab, Evanston, IL, USA

2017 - 2019

PI: Klinton Bicknell

- Researched how linguistic predictability, measured with neural language models, affects sentence processing via eye-tracking.
- Investigated autism diagnoses using linguistic markers, using semantic similarity (word vectors) and pragmatic deficiencies.

#### Research Assistant, CUNY Speech Lab, New York, NY, USA

2012-2016

**PI**: Andrew Rosenberg

Managed DARPA-funded initiative to improve security and personal authentication in computer use, by predicting keystroke and language patterns with machine learning algorithms.

Research Assistant, Columbia NLP Group, New York, NY, USA

2006 - 2007

PI: Rebecca Passonneau

## NON-ACADEMIC EMPLOYMENT

PhD Data Science Intern, Vail Systems, Chicago, IL, USA

**Summer 2020** 

• Created experiments to empirically evaluate the quality of text-to-speech (TTS) systems

Software Developer in Test Intern, Microsoft, Redmond, WA, USA Summer 2013

- Developed website (back- and front-end) to diagnose licensing issues with Microsoft products
- Developed decision-making pipeline to aid in issue diagnosis

#### Operations Analyst, Goldman Sachs, Multiple Locations, USA

2008-2011

- Team Leader for Technology Enhancements
- Created software to streamline daily asset delivery workflow, from 3 hours to 25 minutes

#### LANGUAGES

 $\textbf{Computer:} \ \ Java, \ Python, \ R \ (ggplot2, \ plotly, \ lme4), \ C++, \ C\#, \ I\ TEX, \ Beginner \ in \ \{HTML, \ Leave \ Leave$ 

JavaScript, React, CSS}

Human: American Sign Language (ASL), Hebrew, Latin

### Honors and Awards

Incubation Prize, Hack4Rare Hackathon (Recursion Pharmaceuticals & CTF)

Best Paper Award, Cognitive Modeling & Computational Linguistics (CMCL)

Data Science Fellowship, Northwestern University

2016–2017

Google Lime Connect Scholarship-Finalist

Thomas W. Smith Academic Fellowship, CUNY Graduate Center

National Science Foundation, Undergraduate Research Grant, Columbia University

King's Crown Award for Outstanding Leadership, Columbia University

2021

## SELECT PUBLICATIONS

2021 **Goodkind, A.** TypeShift: A User Interface for Visualizing the Typing Production Process. [arXiv paper]

Goodkind, A., Bicknell, K. Local word statistics affect reading times independently of surprisal. [arXiv paper]

- 2020 **Goodkind, A.** An analytic model for human subjective judgements of computer-generated synthetic voice (TTS) quality. Technical Report for Vail Systems. Chicago, IL.
- 2018 Goodkind, A., Lee, M., Martin, G. E., Losh, M., & Bicknell, K. Detecting language impairments in autism: A computational analysis of semi-structured conversations with vector semantics. In *Proceedings of the Inaugural Meeting of the Society for Computation in Linguistics*. Salt Lake City, UT: Linguistic Society of America. [paper] [slides]
  - Goodkind, A. & Bicknell, K. Predictive power of word surprisal for reading times is a linear function of language model quality. In *Proceedings of the 8th Workshop on Cognitive Modeling and Computational Linguistics (CMCL 2018)*. Salt Lake City, UT: Linguistic Society of America. [paper] [slides]
- 2016 Goodkind, A., Brizan D.G. & Rosenberg, A. Utilizing Overt and Latent Linguistic Structure to Improve Keystroke-Based Authentication. Image and Vision Computing: Best of Biometrics Special Issue.
- 2015 Goodkind, A. & Rosenberg, A. Muddying The Multiword Expression Waters: How Cognitive Demand Affects Multiword Expression Production. 11th Workshop on Multiword Expressions at NAACL-HLT 2015. (Slides)
  - Brizan, D. G.\*, **Goodkind, A.**\*, Koch, P., Balagani, K., Phoha, V. V., & Rosenberg, A. Utilizing Linguistically-Enhanced Keystroke Dynamics to Predict Typist Cognition and Demographics. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, October 2015, vol. 84, 57-68.
- 2008 Goodkind, A. Tracking the Emergence of Narrative Competence in Story Retelling. Quebec Student Journal of Linguistics, Vol. 3.
- 2007 Passonneau, R. J., Goodkind, A., & Levy, E. T. Annotation of Children's Oral Narrations: Modeling Emergent Narrative Skills for Computational Applications. Florida Artificial Intelligence Research Society (FLAIRS), 253-258.

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

# Teaching Assistant

Northwestern University

- Communication Studies 351: Technology & Human Interaction (Prof. Darren Gergle), 2021
- •
- Linguistics 220: Language & Society (Prof. Annette D'Onofrio), 2018
  - Guest lecture on quantitative data analysis
- Cognitive Science 210: Language & the Brain (Profs. Matt Goldrick & Mark Beeman), 2019